Raoul family papers, 1865-1985
Emory University
Raoul family papers,1865-1985
Raoul family.
Manuscript Collection No. 548
20 linear ft. (48 boxes), 11 oversized papers (OP), and 1 oversized bound volume (OBV)
Papers of the Raoul family including letters, journals, writings, photographs, financial and legal records, clippings, printed material, and memorabilia documenting two generations of this large and active Georgia family.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Gift, from various sources.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply: OP2a is restricted for preservation purposes.
Biographical Note
The Raoul family was centered in Georgia, primarily Savannah and Atlanta, although family members resided in other places at various times. The principal family members represented in the collection are William Greene Raoul (1843-1913), railroad president, his wife Mary Wadley Raoul (1848-1936), her sister Sarah Lois Wadley (1844-1920), and the ten children of William Greene and Mary Raoul.
William Greene Raoul (W.G.) and Mary Raoul were married October 27, 1868 in Savannah, Georgia. Between the years 1870 and 1890, eleven children were born to them. In addition to the ten surviving children, the couple had a sixth son, Edward Raoul, who died in 1882 at age two. The family first lived in the home of W. G. Raoul's father in Independence, Louisiana, where W. G. was associated with the Southern Car Works, a family railcar-building enterprise. When the Car Works failed in 1870, W. G. Raoul went to Georgia to work for his father-in-law on the Central of Georgia Railroad. For the ten years between 1870 and 1881, the family made its home in various places in middle Georgia, settling in Macon after 1874. In 1881, the Raouls moved to Savannah, where they lived in a house on the corner of Charlton and Abercorn Streets. During their seven-year residency in Savannah, the family made yearly summer pilgrimages to the cooler climates of north Georgia, the North Carolina mountains, and Martha's Vineyard. After a summer spent in Asheville in 1886, the family chose that city as a permanent summer home and site of their hotel complex, Albemarle Park.
In 1888, the Raouls moved to New York and established themselves in rented houses on Staten Island. After four years in New York, they returned to Georgia, this time to Atlanta where they settled permanently in 1892. There they took an active role in the civic and social life of the city.
Both sons and daughters made their debuts into Atlanta society and family members involved themselves in a variety of social and charitable organizations. Although not active in church work, the family maintained ties to the Episcopal Church. The Raoul residence until 1914 was a large home on Peachtree Street designed for them by noted New York architect Bradford Gilbert in 1891. After her husband's death in 1913, Mary Wadley Raoul built a new house on Lullwater Road in Atlanta's Druid Hills subdivision. She occupied this home until her death in 1936 when its ownership passed to Eleonore Raoul.
The ten children of W. G. and Mary Wadley Raoul pursued varied and often unusual careers. Mary Wadley Raoul (Millis) (b. 1870) became associated with the Socialist Party in the early twentieth century and chaired the Angelo Herndon Freedom Committee (1933). The first son, W. G. Raoul, Jr. (b. 1872), after ventures in textiles and manufacturing, also embraced socialism before making and losing a fortune in the stock market in the 1920's. Gaston C. Raoul (1874-1960) became head of a refrigerator and furniture manufacturing concern in Chattanooga. After contracting tuberculosis at the age of twenty, Thomas Wadley Raoul (1876-1953) traveled seeking cures and later established a permanent residence in Asheville, North Carolina. Rebecca Raoul (b. 1878) devoted time to charity work and to the League of Women Voters.
Agnes Raoul (1882-1914) married Atlanta businessman Thomas K. Glenn and was active in civic and social affairs. Rosine Raoul (1885-1918) also contracted tuberculosis while in her early twenties and spent many of the last years of her life in sanatoriums. Loring Raoul (b. 1887) served in France during World War I, afterwards establishing a large farming enterprise in Florida. The youngest daughter, Eleonore Raoul (b. 1888), was active in the organization of the Equal Suffrage Party of Georgia and supported equal rights for women throughout her life. Please note that Eleonore Raoul changed the spelling of her first name from Eleanore to the French form, Eleonore in 1912. Eleonore Raoul Greene is referred to throughout this descriptive inventory as Eleonore Raoul because of her own practice of using her maiden name throughout most of her life. The youngest child, Norman Raoul (b. 1890), served as an artilleryman with the American Expeditionary Forces in France in World War I, then settled as a businessman in Chattanooga.
Detailed biographical information on the family can be found in Mary Raoul Millis's 1943 memoir, The Family of Raoul (CS71/R22/1943). A photocopy of this work is filed in Series 4 of the collection.
Scope and Content Note
The Raoul family papers contain letters, journals, writings, photographs, financial and legal records, clippings, printed material, and memorabilia documenting two generations of this large and active Georgia family. Family letters comprise approximately two thirds of the entire collection. The earliest original item is a letter of Mary Wadley Raoul dating from 1865 and the most recent are letters to Eleonore Raoul from 1982. The great majority of the papers, however, span the forty years between 1880 and 1920 and provide a relatively complete account of the life of the family during this period.
The papers are arranged in four series. The largest, Series 1, Letters and Personal Papers, is divided into thirteen subseries, each organized around one of the individual family members identified in the biographical note above. Letters written by each family member are grouped with other personal papers in the subseries named for that individual. Most of the correspondence is between the children and Mary Wadley Raoul. Series 2 contains the family photographs; Series 3, financial and legal papers; and Series 4, miscellaneous materials relating to the family as a whole and items that were added to the collection during processing.
The Raoul family papers document the life of the family as a unit in Macon, Savannah, Atlanta, and Bolingbroke, Georgia, Staten Island, New York, and Asheville, North Carolina, and the lives of the children in the various places where they settled. Topics frequently mentioned in the correspondence include births and deaths, domestic matters, courtship and marriage, child raising, social events, health and illness, associations with relatives, and relationships between family members. The childhood and education of the ten Raoul children are well documented. Travel is another major subject covered in the papers. Raoul family members traveled extensively; many of the letters record visits to Bolingbroke, Asheville, New York, Mexico, Europe, and numerous other places. Business activities of the Raoul men are often discussed as well. Topics include railroad and railroad-related operations in the South and Mexico, cotton, shipping, and manufacturing concerns in Georgia and Chattanooga, and real estate ventures in Asheville. An indication of the family's property holdings and other assets is provided by the financial records. Other special subjects include Mary Raoul Millis' and William Greene Raoul, Jr.'s involvement with the Socialist Party, Eleonore Raoul's work with the woman's suffrage movement and the League of Women Voters, and Tom and Rosine Raoul's battles with tuberculosis. The collection also contains information on the Wadley family.
Prominent correspondents represented in the papers include Joseph Emerson Brown, William Jennings Bryan, Carrie Lane Chapman Catt, Porfirio Diaz, William Berry Hartsfield, Atticus Greene Haygood, Alice Paul, and Thomas Edward Watson.
Arrangement Note
Organized into four series: (1) Letters and personal papers, (2) Photographs, (3) Financial and legal papers, and (4) Miscellaneous.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Brown, Joseph E. (Joseph Emerson), 1821-1894.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947.; Diaz, Porfirio, 1830-1915.; Hartsfield, William Berry.; Haygood, Atticus G. (Atticus Greene), 1839-1896.; Millis, Mary Raoul, 1870-1958.; Motes, Columbus W. (Columbus Washington); Raoul, Agnes, 1882-1914.; Raoul, Eleanore, 1888-1983.; Raoul, Gaston C., 1874-1960.; Raoul, Loring, 1887-1976.; Raoul, Mary Wadley, 1848-1936.; Raoul, Norman, 1890-1936.; Raoul, Rebecca Barnard, 1878-1962.; Raoul, Rosine, 1885-1918.; Raoul, Thomas Wadley, 1876-1953.; Raoul, William Greene, 1843-1913.; Raoul, William Greene, 1872-; Senior, Clarence Ollson, 1903-1974.; Wadley, Sarah Lois, 1844-1920.
Corporate Names
American Civil Liberties Union.; Central of Georgia Railway.; Culver Military Academy.; Kentucky Union Railway.; Lawrenceville School.; League of Women Voters (U.S.); Mexican National Railroad Company.; Socialist Party (U.S.); University of Georgia.; Vassar College.; Veltin School (New York, N.Y.); Woodberry Forest School.
Topical Terms
Civil rights--United States.; Cotton--Georgia.; Military education--Indiana.; Mills and mill-work--Georgia.; Political parties--Alabama.; Political parties--Georgia.; Political parties--Montana.; Socialist parties--United States.; Race relations.; Railroads--Georgia.; Railroads--Kentucky.; Railroads--Mexico.; Real property--North Carolina.; Sanatoriums.; Schools--New Jersey.; Schools--New York (State)--New York.; Schools--Virginia.; Shipping--Georgia.; Tuberculosis--Georgia.; Universities and colleges--Georgia.; Universities and colleges--New York (State); Voyages and travels--19th-20th centuries.; Women--Suffrage--Georgia.; Women in politics--United States.; Women in politics--Societies, etc.; Women's colleges--New York (State)
Geographic Names
Alabama--Politics and government.; Athens (Ga.)--Education--Universities and colleges.; Cuba--Description and travel.; Culver (Ind.)--Education--Military schools.; East Asia--Description and travel.; Georgia--Agriculture--Cotton.; Georgia--Business, industries, and trades.; Georgia--Education--Universities and colleges.; Georgia--Politics and government--1865-1950.; Georgia--Politics and government--1951-; Georgia--Race relations.; Georgia--Transportation--Railroads.; Georgia--Women's suffrage.; Indiana--Education--Schools.; Kentucky--Transportation--Railroads.; Lawrenceville (N.J.)--Education--Schools.; Montana--Politics and government.; Mexico--Description and travel.; Mexico--Transportation--Railroads.; New Jersey--Education--Schools.; New York (N.Y.)--Description and travel.; New York (N.Y.)--Education--Schools.; New York (State)--Education--Universities and colleges.; Orange (Va.)--Education--Schools.; Poughkeepsie (N.Y.)--Education--Universities and colleges.; Virginia--Education--Schools.
Form/Genre Terms
Diaries.; Genealogies.; Photographs.
Occupation
Businessmen.; Industrialists.; Suffragettes.
Finding Aid Note
A personal name index to selected correspondents is available.
Related Materials in Other Repositories
The original Wadley diaries are held by the Southern Historical Collection of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, which also holds William Greene Raoul, Jr.'s autobiography, "The Rolling Stone." The Atlanta Historical Society has a small collection of Raoul family papers and the Georgia Department of Archives and History has scrapbooks (on microfilm) donated by Eleonore Raoul relating to her service with the Atlanta League of Women Voters.
Related Materials in This Repository
Letterbooks of William Greene Raoul (MSS162) and the diaries of Sarah L. Wadley (MSS461).
Description of Series
- Letters and personal papers, 1865-1982, Series 1; Boxes 1-35, OP 1-2
  Scope and Content Note
  The series consists of letters written by individual Raoul family members and their other personal papers from 1865-1982. Letters written by the named individual to other family members are generally arranged in chronological order at the beginning of each subseries; letters written to persons outside the family, correspondence received, and other personal papers follow. Photographs of individuals and families are in Series 2; legal and financial records for individual family members may be found in Series 3.
  Arrangement Note
  The series is organized into thirteen subseries representing each of the following persons: (1.1) William Greene Raoul papers, (1.2) Mary Wadley Raoul papers, (1.3) Sarah Lois Wadley papers, (1.4) Mary Raoul Millis papers, (1.5) William Greene Raoul, Jr. papers, (1.6) Gaston C. Raoul papers, (1.7) Thomas Wadley Raoul papers, (1.8) Rebecca Barnard Raoul papers, (1.9) Agnes Raoul papers, (1.10) Rosine Raoul papers, (1.11) Loring Raoul papers, (1.12) Eleonore Raoul papers, and (1.13) Norman Raoul papers.
  - William Greene Raoul paper, 1875-1913, Subseries 1.1; Personal name.; Boxes 1-2
    Biographical Note
    William Greene (W.G.) Raoul was the son of Gaston Turner (born Gaston Cesar Raoul de Champmanoir) and Emily (Davidson) Raoul. Born July 4, 1843, and raised in Livingston Parish, Louisiana, he served with the Washington Artillery, a New Orleans regiment, during the Civil War, achieving the rank of Captain in 1864. He remained in Louisiana after the war to operate the family's railcar construction business until its failure in 1870. That year, under the auspices of his father-in-law William Wadley, Raoul moved to Georgia to begin his career with the Central of Georgia Railway Company. Between 1870 and 1880, he held various positions within the Central system, including roadmaster, superintendent, and vice-president. In 1883, he was elected to succeed William Wadley as president of the Central, a post he held until 1887 when he was defeated for the office by E. P. Alexander. He subsequently served as president of the Mexican National Railway Company (1887-1904), the Atlantic and Birmingham Railway Company (1902-1905), and the Southwestern Railroad (1901-1913). Raoul actively supported the work of the Associated Charities of Atlanta and established the W. G. Raoul Foundation to combat tuberculosis in Georgia. He died in Atlanta on January 17, 1913 and is buried in Westview Cemetery.
    For an account of Raoul's association with the Central of Georgia Railway Company, see Maury Klein's, The Great Richmond Terminal, 1970 (HE2771/Al3K53).
    William Greene Raoul's papers include letters to his family, primarily to his wife, Mary Wadley Raoul, and his eldest daughter, Mary Raoul Millis (1882-1907); general and business correspondence (1875-1905); and miscellaneous materials mainly relating to his railroad career.
    W. G. Raoul's letters to his wife concern his travels, family matters, his children's development, the development of Albemarle Park in Asheville, business ventures of his sons, and Tom's tuberculosis. There is also some coverage of his business activities.
    William Raoul's earliest letters to daughter Mary question her about her acquaintances and the quality of her education (1886-1887). Long letters from Cuba and Mexico discuss his unfavorable impression of the natives and his difficulties in learning the language. Later letters comment on his support of bi-metalism (1895-1896) and national politics (1896).
    The general correspondence consists mainly of letters to Raoul and relates primarily to W. G. Raoul's business interests, particularly the Central of Georgia Railway Company. The bulk dates from the time of his controversial election as president of the Central (1882-1883), and includes numerous letters of congratulation. Other correspondence concerns his subsequent loss of the presidency (1886), his attempt to be appointed a U.S. Railroad Commissioner (1887), his election to the presidency of the Mexican National Railway Company (1887), his Civil War service (1905), William Jennings Bryan's visit to Atlanta (1907), and the death mask of Napoleon owned by Raoul (1909). Letters to Raoul from various relatives, including his father are also contained here. Prominent correspondents include E. P. Alexander, Augustus 0. Bacon, Joseph E. Brown, William Jennings Bryan, Porfirio Diaz, Atticus Greene Haygood, Leander Newton Trammell, William Wadley, and Tom Watson. Miscellaneous materials relate to Raoul's car-axle box invention, the Mexican National Railway Company, and Raoul 's death in 1913.
    Arranged by record type.
    - Letters, 1882-1907
    - 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1884-1886 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1887-1890 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1892-1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1899, January-May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1899, August-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1900, February-June (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1900, July-December (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1901, January-March (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1901, July-December (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1902, January-June (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1902, July-September (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1905-1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - General correspondence and miscellaneous
    - General correspondence, 1875-1883, January 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence, 1883, January 3-1884 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence, 1886-1889 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - General correspondence, 1890-1904 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - General correspondence, 1905-1909 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Car-axle box patents and papers, 1881-1882 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Clippings re career (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Mexican National Railway Company - miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Last Will and Testament, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Obituaries, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Resolutions passed at his death, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mary Wadley Raoul papers, 1865-1936, Subseries 1.2; Personal name.; Boxes 3-4
    The daughter of Georgia railroad executive, William Morrill Wadley and Rebecca Barnard (Everingham) Wadley, Mary Wadley Raoul was born March 4, 1848. Before her marriage to William Greene Raoul in 1868, she lived in Savannah and Monroe, Louisiana. She attended school briefly in Cave Spring, Floyd County, Georgia, in 1866. The twenty years between 1870 and 1890 were spent raising her ten children in Macon, Savannah, and New York. After the family settled in Atlanta in 1892, Mary became active in a number of civic and social organizations. She served on the board of the Cotton States and International Exposition in 1895, was a charter member of the Every Saturday Club, and maintained memberships in the Daughters of the American Revolution and the United Daughters of the Confederacy. She was also involved in promoting the Free Kindergarten movement in Atlanta and one of the city's early kindergartens was named for her. She died August 1, 1936 in Atlanta.
    Papers of Mary Wadley Raoul include letters to her family (1865-1935), letters from relatives and friends (1884-1935), and a small group of miscellaneous materials. Most of the early Mary Raoul letters are to her husband and concern the children and family activities (1870-1886). Letters from 1886 through May 1907 are primarily to her daughter Mary Raoul Millis. These letters give news of family events, including the Central of Georgia election (1886-1887) and her own unwanted pregnancy (1888). After Mary's marriage to John Millis in 1893, letters offer advice on setting up housekeeping, clothes and sewing, managing servants, detecting pregnancy, family health problems, weddings, travels, William Jr.'s failures, her own depression (1904), and the death of Ruth Cunningham Raoul (1905). Beginning in June 1907, most of the letters are to her sister Sarah Wadley. Several of the letters relate to her support of the suffrage movement (1915-1919), including one written from the 1915 national convention in Washington, D.C.
    The incoming letters are primarily from relatives. Miscellaneous materials include a journal she kept from 1872-1876 reporting mainly on the childhoods of her eldest children, Mary and William, Jr.
    - Letters, 1865-1936
    - 1865-1881 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1882-1884 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1885-1886, May (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1886, July-September (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1886, October-December (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1887, January-March (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1887, April-June (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1889-1893 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1894-1896 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1897-1898 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1899-1900 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1901-1903 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1904 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 1905-1906 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1907 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1914-1915 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1918 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1919, January-May (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1919, June-December (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1920 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Letters from various persons, 1884-1906 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Letters from various persons, 1907-1925 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Letters from various persons, 1926-1936 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Other papers
    - Journal, 1872-1876 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Address to the Every Saturday History Class, December 1916 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Sarah Lois Wadley papers, 1874-1920, Subseries 1.3; Personal name.; Boxes 5-10
    Older sister of Mary Wadley Raoul, Sarah L. Wadley was born November 26, 1844 at the home of her Wadley grandparents in New Market, New Hampshire. After several years of residence in various places in Georgia and Louisiana she moved with her parents to a large plantation, "Great Hill Place," near Bolingbroke, Monroe County, Georgia in 1873. She remained there for the rest of her life, caring for her mother until the latter's death in 1905. Sarah Wadley died December 7, 1920.
    While the majority of the letters among the papers of Sarah L. Wadley are from Sarah to her sister Mary, a number are to her brother-in-law, W. G. Raoul, and to her Raoul nieces and nephews. The subseries also contains a small group of letters to Sarah Wadley from other relatives and friends and typescript extracts from her diary (1859-1862). [Diaries on microfilm in Sarah L. Wadley papers in this department.]
    Written primarily from Great Hill Place, Sarah Wadley's letters provide a nearly unbroken account of Wadley family activities from 1874 to her death in 1920. The Raoul children were frequent visitors to Great Hill Place and Sarah often stayed with them in Atlanta during their parents' absence. The letters concern their activities, health and development, romances and marriages, business problems, and families.
    Many of the letters describe domestic life and others report on the health of her mother, Rebecca B. Wadley, and her own poor health. Other letters concern her travels, the death of her mother (1905), the disposition of Great Hill Place (1907, 1917), and women's suffrage and voting (1917-1920). Sarah Wadley's letters to W. G. Raoul discuss her editorial assistance to him with Central of Georgia reports, Raoul's loss of the presidency of the Central, other railroad affairs, family finances, and her father, William M. Wadley.
    - Letters, 1874-1891
    - 1874-1875 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1877-1883 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1884-1885 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1886 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1887 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1888 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1889 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1890, January-June (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1890, July-December (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1891, January-April (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1891, May-December (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 1892, January-July (Box 6, Folder 1)